‫In this tutorial, we're going to install Python onto the Windows operating system.
‫The burning question here is probably why do I need to install Python?
‫The whole point of downloading Python is that it provides us all the tools that allows the computer
‫to interact with the Python programming language so that it can execute our code or run our code.
‫This is Windows 11.
‫This process should work on Windows ten so you can follow along if you're running Windows ten or 11.
‫So here I have a fresh installation of Windows 11.
‫So let's go ahead and open up a browser window, gave it to Google and let's type in Python download.
‫So there is only one place where we want to download Python safely, and that is the Python website.
‫So let's head over to Python dot org.
‫You can go there directly and let's go over to downloads.
‫So you can see by default when you navigate your land on the page, we are presented with the Python
‫download and that is the latest version.
‫So for this course I am running 3.9.5.
‫But if you're running windows you can run any version of Python from about 3.4.
‫So let's head over to the download section.
‫Let's go to Windows and have a look at the different options here.
‫Now, we've already noticed that there are different versions of Python.
‫Python is a very proactive language which is constantly being updated, although at the moment that's
‫not necessarily an important factor.
‫But later along the line in your development, you may be working with legacy software.
‫That software may be written with older versions of Python, so you may have a need in the future to
‫download different versions and use different versions of Python when developing applications.
‫For this course.
‫All the examples are demonstrated utilizing Python 3.9.5.
‫And although I suggested that that isn't necessarily an issue if you're running later or earlier versions
‫of Python for this particular course, if you do want to follow along and download that version, let's
‫go ahead and search this page here for 3.9.5 and download the correct version.
‫Okay, So clicking on the link here, we're presented with a few different options at the bottom here
‫we can download the 64 bit or 32 bit option.
‫Now, if you're running in a computer that's been purchased over the last ten years, then the likelihood
‫is that you're running a 64 bit machine.
‫So you go ahead and download 64 bit.
‫Once you've downloaded Python, let's just go ahead and open the file.
‫It will be downloaded, no doubt to the download folder if you don't have this particular operating
‫system.
‫So here we present you with two options Install now and customize installation.
‫The first option that you should select is to add Python 3.9 to path.
‫So by adding Python to PATH, it makes it possible for you to run or use python from your command prompt.
‫And that's something that we want to do.
‫So let's make sure we add and select that option.
‫Secondly, I just want to customize where we are going to actually install Python, because for example,
‫here you can see that it's going to be installed in this location here, but potentially that isn't
‫necessarily a very convenient place where I want to actually store the Python installation, because
‫if I've got multiple versions of Python, maybe I want to be able to easily access those different versions.
‫So I like to install Python directly onto the C drive so we can ignore this list here.
‫We can install everything that isn't a problem for this particular course.
‫So I press next and then here customize the installation I'm just going to remove.
‫Everything and then make sure that then that is then installed onto the C drive in a folder called Python
‫three nine referencing the version of Python.
‫So you can decide if you want to install for all users.
‫But like I said, there's not really anything else here that we need to consider for this particular
‫course.
‫So you can just go ahead now and install.
‫So do you want to make changes?
‫Yes.
‫So once we're finished, we're told it was successful, so everything should be absolutely fine.
‫So we just close that.
‫Installer.
‫Looks like I've opened it up twice now.
‫If you do have any problems with installing Python, then head over to Stack Overflow if you haven't
‫been introduced or seen Stack Overflow before.
‫It is a service whereby you can ask technical questions.
‫If you're having problems with a software installation, maybe you're having problems with some code
‫that you're working on.
‫Then definitely have a look at Stack Overflow because generally 99% of the time, the problems that
‫you're experiencing, someone else has already experienced those.
‫So it's likely to be a resolution for that problem here.
‫So let's just check that python has been installed so we can go over to start.
‫Let's type in the word command.
‫That should bring up the command prompt here or give us the option to open up the command prompt and
‫then from inside the command prompt.
‫Well, open that from inside the command prompt.
‫I'm going to type in P for Python space, dash, dash and then version.
‫So that's going to tell me that Python 3.95 is now installed on the computer.
‫With Python now installed, we're now ready to develop and execute or run our applications in Python.