‫Before you start this set up installation guide, we're making the assumption that you have Python installed.
‫If you don't, then check out the previous tutorial where we take you through those steps.
‫In this course.
‫Our preferred code editor is Visual Studio Code.
‫All the examples in this course will be presented utilizing this software.
‫Although it's completely optional what code editor you choose.
‫We do recommend that you follow along with this course with Visual Studio Code.
‫So let's start by browsing or searching for Visual Studio Code.
‫We can use the keyword download as well.
‫That can be handy.
‫That should take us to code Visual Studio download.
‫So let's go over to that web page.
‫Looks a little bit like this, except that.
‫So from here you can see that we've got multiple options.
‫Visual Studio Code can be installed and used on multiple operating systems.
‫Now, assuming that you have a computer that's been purchased over the last ten years, the likelihood
‫is that you're running a 64 bit operating system.
‫So you can select these 64 bit set up installer here, this 64 bit option here, or you can just go
‫ahead and select this Windows download, whichever one you decide.
‫That should be absolutely fine.
‫So this download here is going to be a universal installer for Windows eight, ten and 11.
‫Okay, so I'm clicking on that page.
‫You can see that we've started downloading, so that would take a couple of seconds and then we can
‫start.
‫So let's quickly run through the installation wizard here.
‫So accept the agreement.
‫Press Next, you can decide where you want to install Visual Studio code.
‫I don't recommend that you change the installation settings there unless you have some specific setup
‫on your computer.
‫So just next, the Start menu folder.
‫Just next.
‫And then let's create a desktop icon that can be handy and add to path that is always going to be handy
‫so we can utilize a terminal effectively as press next and install.
‫Once you've finished installing Visual Studio Code, go ahead and open up Visual Studio Code.
‫I'm just going to take you through a few different settings that you can apply and give you a basic
‫introduction to Visual Studio Code if you're completely new to this.
‫So first of all, we need to select what we want it to look like.
‫So I'm just going to select the dark option here.
‫Next selection here.
‫There isn't really anything here that we need to consider, so let's just close that tab.
‫Right?
‫So first of all, if we want to create a new project with Visual Studio Code or if you want to work
‫with the project, then we generally open up the folder and work within that folder.
‫So what we're going to need to do here very briefly is let's go over to a desktop here.
‫Let's just create a new folder.
‫Let's just call this project.
‫So generally you have a project folder, that's the folder where your project is being developed, all
‫the files, etc. is going to be in that folder.
‫So generally when we open up a new Visual Studio code window or project, the first step is to open
‫the folder.
‫We can do that by the left hand side.
‫Here we have the Explorer tab here or you can go to file and then open folder.
‫So we just need to select the folder, our project folder, and now we have the project folder on the
‫left hand side here.
‫So we're interacting with that folder we just created on the desktop.
‫So if we were to create a new file, so all python files have the PY file extension, you can see we've
‫created a new file there.
‫So if I go back to the folder we created on the desktop, you can see that that folder now has that
‫file we've just created so you can see how that's interacting with that folder.
‫All right.
‫So that's my project.
‫And the idea here is that we click on the file, it appears on the right hand side here, we can start
‫writing some code.
‫You can see that Visual Studio code uses a TAB system.
‫So when we open up new files, you'll be able to access those files from the top ribbon ribbon here.
‫So.
‫On the right hand side.
‫This can be pretty handy here.
‫We can split the screen so you can work on two files.
‫That's pretty handy if you're working with multiple files, and we can close that.
‫So go ahead and close the file.
‫That would then close that additional window.
‫So you notice here and it's very small at the moment or maybe on your screen, but you can see a dot
‫next to the name with the file that we've opened.
‫That DOT represents the fact that the file has not been saved.
‫Now, one of the common problems that I find students fall into at the start is they forget to save
‫their files.
‫Now, I recommend that you go over to file and you select Auto Save.
‫So just click on Auto Save and that will just auto save.
‫Now all the files so you'd never have to press save any time you type something, it would just automatically
‫save.
‫And that can be really handy.
‫Something else that you'll probably want to do is to zoom in or utilize the will mouse to zoom in.
‫So if you go over to file and then preferences and then settings, that's where you're going to find
‫all the settings for Visual Studio code.
‫But if I type in, zoom into this search bar up top here, I can select Zoom.
‫And now what I can do is I can easily zoom when holding the control key and my mouse if I can find the
‫control key.
‫Of course.
‫There we go.
‫So there we go.
‫So it makes it a lot easier for you to zoom in and out, which can be very handy.
‫In addition to that, if you hold down control and press plus and minus on your keyboard, you can actually
‫scale the whole UI of Visual Studio code.
‫The last feature, which is going to be utilized on this course is the terminal.
‫Now, if I dragged from the bottom just before the blue bar at the bottom, you can't see that, but
‫you can kind of see where my mouse is ended here.
‫Just here.
‫The new arrow appears up and down.
‫Our appears when it's available.
‫And it means I can drag up and I can drag this terminal up with my mouse here.
‫So this opens up the terminal.
‫This is really handy feature that we're going to be utilizing throughout this course.
‫And generally when you're working with Django or Python.
‫The terminal is normally needed for some reason, so I can access that terminal by dragging it up.
‫Now there is a shortcut if I go to view, you can see here, we're told in the terminal I need to press
‫control plus and it looks like a left single quote that is a shortcut to bring the terminal up and down.
‫So control plus I think I have it on this keyboard.
‫I'm using a mac keyboard now.
‫It's not going to work.
‫Okay, So on your keyboard, you can type in your shortcut.
‫Now, let me just zoom back out again.
‫Okay?
‫So if you do want to remove the terminal, there is a bin here which I click and then that removes the
‫terminal and closes the terminal window.
‫So just make sure that you feel comfortable opening and closing the terminal wherever you drag or wherever
‫you use the shortcut.
‫I do recommend that you spend maybe five, 10 minutes just familiarizing yourself with Visual Studio
‫Code because it can make following the tutorials much easier.