‫When working with Python and Visual Studio Code, the likelihood is that you're going to be working
‫within virtual environments.
‫When you download Python, it comes with all the tools to allow you to start virtual environments on
‫your computer.
‫In this tutorial we focus on the process.
‫So do try and move away from asking yourself lots of questions.
‫Why do I need a virtual environment?
‫What is a virtual environment?
‫And just focus on the process at this point?
‫Within your course Core content.
‫Additional information regarding the virtual environment will be provided if appropriate.
‫Before you start this process, you will need Visual Studio code and Python installed.
‫So here on Windows, we've already installed Visual Studio Code.
‫Check out the previous tutorials if you haven't already done so.
‫All right.
‫So here we have a project.
‫It's automatically opened up my project, so let's just go through that process again.
‫So the first thing we want to do.
‫File open a folder, open the project that we want to work with.
‫So we have a project folder on the desktop.
‫We've opened that up and you can see that we have this file.
‫Okay, so now we want to build a virtual environment.
‫Like I mentioned, when we download Python, one of the tools that it comes with is the virtual environment.
‫So we can go ahead and type PI for Python and then we can use the RM flag VM V to start the actual virtual
‫environment.
‫And then we need to then pass in the name of the folder.
‫So this folder can be absolutely anything.
‫So let's just call this VM V.
‫So this command will then start a new virtual environment.
‫You can see that we've created a folder with lots of other information or folders and files inside of
‫that.
‫To start to paint a picture of what's going on here.
‫Imagine your computer is a box.
‫When we download Python, Python is installed in that box.
‫If we wanted to run python, we could run python from that box.
‫Our operating system.
‫Now, the problem is here, when we start working on multiple projects, each project may require a
‫different additional software.
‫So for example, one project might be utilizing Django, maybe Django four, and one project might be
‫utilizing Django 3.2 and an earlier version of Django.
‫Now, the problem is here in our main box, if we were to install Django four and Django 3.2, for example,
‫in the same box, potentially we would have conflicts.
‫So the whole idea here of a virtual environment is that we make smaller boxes inside of our big box.
‫So we create virtual environments within our computer, within that virtual environment we install or
‫we have Python available and we can install additional software inside of that smaller box.
‫That way we can encapsulate everything that the project requires.
‫That particular project requires inside of that smaller box without conflicting or damaging or changing
‫the main big box, our main operating system.
‫So we're working within a smaller box, within the bigger box here, and that allows us to create specific
‫environments for specific projects that we're working within.
‫So what we've done here is we've created our virtual environment.
‫Now what we need to do is we need to activate it.
‫So on Windows, we just need to type in V Now I'm going to press tab here.
‫Notice that it's going to end the it's not going to end it.
‫It's going to end the command.
‫So V And then I press tab and you can see here finishes off the line and that references the folder
‫here inside of here we have a folder called Scripts.
‫So inside of this folder we have scripts, so we're just navigating this folder system here.
‫I press tab and then I need to activate.
‫So inside of scripts we have activate and I press tab to finish off that line or that command and press
‫enter and you can see that we have a problem.
‫Not everyone will experience this problem, but we need to change some of the settings to allow us to
‫actually start a virtual environment.
‫If you received this issue here, we just need to configure the execution policies on your computer.
‫Now, there's a few different ways of doing this.
‫If you go over to Stack Overflow like I previously mentioned in the previous tutorial.
‫Good place to resolve any issues that we might have.
‫There are a few different methods of doing this, so let's just follow this one here.
‫So we need to set execution policy and restricted scope process as mentioned in the section in your
‫PowerShell window.
‫So we need to open up a PowerShell window.
‫So let's go to start, let's type in PowerShell.
‫Now we're going to need to open up a PowerShell window to again PowerShell window.
‫We are going to need to do that as administrator.
‫So I right click and then I select run as administrator.
‫So that's going to open up PowerShell as an administrator.
‫So now what we can do is we can run this command, so set dash execution policy and restrict escape
‫process.
‫So I'm going to copy that.
‫This link will be available in the in the resources of this tutorial.
‫So let's go ahead and paste that in, give that a go.
‫So I need to now press Y or A to yes to Oh so I type in Capital A and press enter and there we go.
‫So now what we need to do is we just need to close Visual Studio code.
‫This is a step that some forget or don't do, and we can then go ahead and just open up Visual Studio
‫code once again.
‫I think there's a shortcut on my desktop for that.
‫And now let's go through the process again.
‫So the virtual environment is still there.
‫Whenever we start a new, whenever we come back to our project, you can see that the folder that was
‫the path here correlates to the folder of our project.
‫So we're inside of this folder.
‫So if I type in, let's just clear this.
‫So I type in clear and enter to clear the screen.
‫If I type in LRS, we can see that that shows me the current folder that I'm working within because
‫I can see the files and folders that correlate to my project here.
‫So I press clear again.
‫Now I can just press up that brings, brings up the previous commands up and down.
‫So I give that a go that makes things a little bit easier.
‫So I clear the screen again.
‫So let's now start or try to activate our virtual environment again.
‫So here I'm going to type in V press tab, then Capital S tab A tab.
‫And there we go.
‫So you can see that that method did not work.
‫So that familiarize yourself with the process if you like.
‫So let's go back into the PowerShell.
‫Let's try again.
‫PowerShell.
‫Right click.
‫Run as administrator Press.
‫Yes.
‫And let's go ahead and press and type in set execution policy.
‫I'm restricted and then dash force.
‫So that's what we're going to run here.
‫Okay, so I've just changed the scale of my font here so you can actually see the command.
‫That should make it a lot easier for it.
‫So let's press enter there and let's now give this a go.
‫So I'm restricted force so there are no messages here.
‫So let's go back into Visual Studio Code.
‫Let's go ahead and close the PowerShell.
‫Let's open this up again, view terminal and then let's give this a go again.
‫So I just press up here twice to the command to activate virtual environment.
‫You can type it in.
‫Of course I press enter and you can see that this time we then have access now to run the virtual environment.
‫So you can see here at the start of this command line I have VM V and that indicates the fact that I'm
‫now working in the virtual environment.
‫So step one is to create a virtual environment.
‫Step two is always then to activate it.
‫So before you start working on your project, you need to make sure that you access or activate sorry,
‫the virtual environment.
‫So we can deactivate the environment.
‫So if I press up to bring up the previous command, press D and then press tab to finish stuff off the
‫command line there, press enter.
‫You can see that that does not deactivate the virtual environment.
‫So if I just close the window and then I open up again, you can see by doing that I then deactivated
‫the virtual environment.
‫So.
‫That's how to activate and then potentially deactivate the virtual environment.
‫There are other variations here, but that's just a quick and simple way of working, similar to overcoming
‫the problem that we have previously.
‫There are many different variations of performing and working in a way that kind of avoids that problem.
‫But I've just shown you one of many ways that is possible.
‫So again, I do recommend that you spend a little bit of time, maybe five, 10 minutes, just familiarizing
‫yourself with that process, starting, stopping, maybe make some notes regarding the commands that
‫you need because you are going to pretty much create a virtual environment or start a virtual environment
‫every time you work with a Python application, specifically Django applications.