‫The core of arguably all web applications are robust data models and data handling.
‫In a Django project, the Django Forum is a core component abstracted away from view, which enables
‫developers to rapidly create applications that require interactions with databases and its data.
‫In this course at Level one, we begin our journey learning how to interact with a database from a DJANGO
‫project.
‫This course has one aim, and that is to introduce to you the fundamental Django erm concepts so that
‫you can start to generate applications that interact with databases.
‫Although you could complete this course as a complete beginner to Django, it would be more beneficial
‫for you to have some familiarity with creating and starting a Django project.
‫We do provide some initial guides on how to start a Django project and just familiarize yourself with
‫the basics of Django in this course.
‫And that's an optional session at the start of this course.
‫Ultimately you are taking this course because you are interested in learning in more detail how Django
‫interacts with the database through the Django Erm, I am Alexander a.k.a Zonda.
‫You may know me from the very Academy YouTube channel.
‫I have the absolute pleasure of being your instructor for this course.
‫Do you take time to browse the course structure, check out the course description and learning outcomes.
‫This will provide more information about the course and course outcomes.
‫Just to finish off, this introduction highlights some of the features of this course.
‫You will find a section main course communication in this section.
‫I will keep you updated with course updates and any other news related to the course.
‫To help aid your learning, you will find multiple choice quizzes at the end of settings in this course.
‫What I've tried to do here is just to encapsulate all the main learning points found within sections
‫and put them in to a quiz and you can utilise this to develop your own notes.
‫Assuming you are completely new to Django or maybe Python, please check out the Preparing for Development
‫or our installation guides there.
‫I take you through the steps needed to install all the software that we're going to be utilizing in
‫this course.
‫Thank you very much for purchasing and I hope you enjoy the course.